Guide to the Elizabeth Brownell Collier Papers, 1895-1968
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Elizabeth Brownell Collier Papers
1895-1968
Collier, Elizabeth Brownell
0.2 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, notes, transcripts, and photographs related to Elizabeth Brownell Collier's turn-of-the-century childhood, as well as her time at Vassar and beyond.
Biographical Note
Elizabeth Brownell Collier was born on December 30, 1883. Her mother, Laura Brownell Collier (VC 1874), was a member of a prominent New England family and her father, John Austin Collier, was a scientist. When she was a young girl, the family moved to Brooklyn, where Laura Collier taught at Packer Collegiate Institute, a private, all-girls academy. Both Elizabeth and her younger sister Katharine attended Packer. Elizabeth graduated from Packer in 1902 and spent a year at the University of Vermont before transferring to Vassar College.
Elizabeth did well at Vassar, where she was named to Phi Beta Kappa and awarded the Furness Prize for best essay on a Shakespearean or Elizabethan subject. In 1909 she found a job teaching English at Hunter College in Manhattan. Elizabeth earned her Master of Arts from Columbia University at 1911 and spent a year studying in Oxford, England.
When she was not at work, Elizabeth spent much of her time doing civic work. She was involved in the suffrage movement, and after women gained the vote, she was appointed Vice President of the New York City League of Women Voters, and Vice Chairman of the Brooklyn Republican Party. Among others, she worked closely with Mayor Fiorello LaGuardia.
After her retirement, Elizabeth moved to Highland, New York, where she lived with an invalid friend, a Miss Grace Roberts. She returned often to visit the Vassar College campus. Elizabeth died on November 30, 1968, in a fire which destroyed her home.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains material related to Elizabeth Brownell Collier's turn-of-the-century childhood, as well as her time at Vassar and beyond. Compared to the rest of the Collier Family Papers, this collection is very small. Most or all of the material was probably saved by Elizabeth's sister Katharine or her mother Laura, since whatever she owned at the time was probably destroyed in the fire in which she died. Elizabeth appears to have been an active and colorful figure who grew eccentric in her old age.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Researchers interested in more of the personal aspects of Laura Brownell Collier's life are encouraged to examine the Class of 1906 Bulletins, as well as the Alumnae/i Biographical Files in the Archives and Special Collections Library:
Elizabeth Brownell Collier File, Alumnae/i Biographical Files
The papers of Elizabeth's sister, Katharine Brownell Collier (VC 1908), and mother, Laura Brownell Collier (VC 1874), are also available for research:
Katharine Brownell Collier Papers
Laura Brownell Collier Papers
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Packer Collegiate Institute, Brooklyn; Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae
Document Types:
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Photographs; Printed ephemera
VCL Categories:
Vassar College; Family
Encoding Information
Encoded by Madeleine Amodio, June 2011. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, June 2025.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lincoln Brownell, circa 1980-1984.
Series List
- Series I. PERSONAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1910, 1925
- Series II. EDUCATIONAL INSTITUTIONS, 1895-1946
- Series III. WRITINGS, circa 1960s
- Series IV. NEWSPAPER ARTICLES, 1906-1968
- Series V. PHOTOGRAPHS, undated
Container List
- Series I. Personal Correspondence
  - Darling, Mollie, 1925; (3 items) (Folder 1.1)
  - Wright, Donald Collier, wedding invitation, (cousin of EBC), 1910; (1 item) (Folder 1.2)
- Series II. Educational Institutions
  - Packer Collegiate Institute
    - Academics: report cards, 1895-1896; (5 items) (Folder 1.3)
    - Annual Report of the President to the Board of Trustees, 1945-1946; (TS, 21 p.) (Folder 1.4)
    - "A Long Way Forward: The First Hundred Years of Packer Collegiate Institute,", 1945; (TS, 2 p.) (Folder 1.5)
  - Vassar College
    - Package notifications, circa 1904-1906; (2 items) (Folder 1.6)
- Series III. Writings
  - Book Reviews Written by Elizabeth Brownell Collier
    - The Doll's Trunk Murder by Helen Reilly, undated; (TS, 1 p., 1 draft) (Folder 1.7)
    - The Egyptian Cross Mystery by Ellery Queen, undated; (TS, 2 p., 1 draft) (Folder 1.8)
    - Peking Picnic by Ann Bridge, undated; (TS, 2 p. 1 draft) (Folder 1.9)
    - The Sheltered Life by Ellen Glasgow, undated; (TS, 2 p., 1 draft) (Folder 1.10)
  - Manuscripts Written by Elizabeth Brownell Collier
    - "A Piece of Ice,", circa 1960s; (MS, 9 p., 1 draft) (Folder 1.11)
- Series IV. Newspaper Articles
  - "Honor Girls at Vassar," "The Furness Prize," sources unknown, 1906; (2 items) (Folder 1.12)
  - "GOP to Name Ticker July 24…Miss Collier Presides," sources: New York World?, 1919 Jun 19; (1 item) (Folder 1.13)
  - "Miss Elizabeth Collier Discusses Prostitution," source unknown, 1927 Jul 16; (3 items) (Folder 1.14)
  - Published review of The Doll's Trunk Murder by Helen Reilly, source unknown, 1932 Dec 19; (1 item) (Folder 1.15)
  - "Professor Collier Reports WAVES Occupy Part of Hunter College," Source: The Burlington Free Press, 1943 Jan 28; (1 item) (Folder 1.16)
  - "Rites Conducted for Miss Collier," Source: Poughkeepsie Journal, 1968 Dec 7; (1 item) (Folder 1.17)
- Series V. Photographs
  - Portrait of EBC in various poses, youthful wearing white blouse and dark skirt, necklace, photographer: Parker, Washington, D.C., undated; (2 items) (Folder 1.18)
  - Portrait of EBC in various poses, youthful wearing white blouse and dark skirt, necklace, photographer: Parker, Washington, D.C., undated; (2 items) (Folder 1.19)
  - Portrait of EBC in various poses, youthful, wearing white blouse and dark skirt, necklace, undated; (2 items) (Folder 1.20)
  - Portrait of EBC in various poses, youthful, wearing white blouse and dark skirt, necklace, undated; (2 items) (Folder 1.21)